<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Syllogologia; or, An historical discourse of parliaments in their originall before the Conquest, and continuance since. Together with the originall growth, and continuance, of these courts following, viz. [brace] High Court of Chancery, Upper Bench, Common-Pleas, Exchequer, Dutchy, and other inferiour courts now in use in this Commonwealth.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S93</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1646_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203463</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863412</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863412</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115614</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115614)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 207:E1646[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Syllogologia; or, An historical discourse of parliaments in their originall before the Conquest, and continuance since. Together with the originall growth, and continuance, of these courts following, viz. [brace] High Court of Chancery, Upper Bench, Common-Pleas, Exchequer, Dutchy, and other inferiour courts now in use in this Commonwealth.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Firby, near Grayes-Inne-Gate in Holborn.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: J.S.</note>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters; the words "High .. Dutchy," are bracketed together, with "viz." reading up at left.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 14.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Legislative bodies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115614:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; OR, An Hiſtorical Diſcourſe OF PARLIAMENTS in their originall before the Conqueſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance ſince.</p>
            <p>Together with the Originall growth, and continuance, of theſe Courts following,</p>
            <list>
               <head>Viz.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>High Court of</hi> CHANCERY,</item>
               <item>UPPER BENCH,</item>
               <item>COMMON-PLEAS,</item>
               <item>EXCHEQUER,</item>
               <item>DUTCHY,</item>
            </list>
            <p>And other inferiour Courts now in uſe in this Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Firby,</hi> near <hi>Grayes-Inne-Gate</hi> in <hi>Holborn.</hi> 1656.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115614:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115614:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115614:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115614:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115614:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His treatiſe, though ſmall, yet hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken a ſubject of a very ſublime nature to handle, the Author being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known (by his perſon, though not for his pains) another hand hath preſumed to inſert a few marginall notes to it, with his authorities for what he ſets down; if thou compare both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, thou wilt find that the notes and the text do help one another: when thou readeſt the book ſome of the notes will ſerve thee as an opened caſement in windows, through which thou mayſt ſee more diſtinctly that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far
<pb facs="tcp:115614:5"/>off which he doth ſee down without citing his Authorities; ſome others of them are as blinds upon windows (not to hinder thy light) but to direct and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell thy eyes upwards towards Antiquity with more Infalabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But take not the Pen-man of the notes as one that herby would detract any thing from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors worth (who ever he be) for it is eaſily ſeen by his Tract that he knew what he writ, and and we know that thoſe who are no Novices in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Learning upon peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of this tract (though many of his authorities are not cited in the very pages) yet can judge of <hi>Hercules</hi> by his foot, and that this Author was of no ordinary ſtature in Antiquity. The notes then are to prevent ſuch as are
<pb facs="tcp:115614:3"/>no great proficients in the ſchool of the Antients from ſaying, That the Authors <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> is the warrant of ſome things he writ, and that it hath no other paſſable or current autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. If thou findeſt faylings here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I have but this to ſay to thee, <hi>Humanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt errare;</hi> and if thou be more than meer man, then let the Author and the World ſee thy perfect work that ſhall be ſubject to no error, and thereby thou wilt gratify mankind more than yet the World hath been Bleſſed with in any thing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Bible. But not to make the Porch bigger than the Church, I deſire thee to be can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, and to read without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell,</salute>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115614:5"/>
            <head>An Hiſtoricall Diſcourſe of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and other Courts &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S without doubt ever ſince the firſt propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Mankind on the face of the earth; there were before the Deluge, <hi>Cain</hi> and Cains and proud Giants, and after the Food, <hi>Cham, Nimrod, Eſau</hi> and ſuch like mighty Hunters, and injurious Oppreſſors of the ſervants of God, ſo from time to time, God out of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal care and mercifull providence, hath excited ſome of his own, indued and armed with Wiſdome, Authority, and power, not only to preſerve his little ones from the greedy and rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous jawes of wicked perſecutors, but alſo after a ſort to reſiſt theire cruelty and chaſtiſe them for their exceſſe and ſury.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115614:6"/>
            <p>For we read in <hi>Geneſis</hi> that <hi>Adam;</hi> immediatly after his Fall, had two ſons <hi>(to wit) Abell</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> whom he taught in the knowledg of God; and <hi>Cain</hi> was a wicked perſon and ſlew his Brother, of which it grieved him not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll God had afflicted him with the fire and torment of his Conſcience, and then he cried out <hi>Maior eſt paena mea quam ut ſuſtinere posſim. Gen.</hi> 4.13. After <hi>Cain,</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Lamech</hi> (born in the houſe of <hi>Cham</hi>) who corrupted the inſtitution of Marriage, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to his Wives <hi>Adah</hi> and <hi>Zilla.</hi> And beſides them, many others lived im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly, even to the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> when all the Earth was corrupted; wherefore God deſtroyed all mankind with the reſt of the Creatures from the face of the Earth, except <hi>Noah</hi> and thoſe that were with him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.23. And againe after that deluge, when the Earth was repleniſhed with a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people, and conſequently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions were become ſo numerous, that there was not found any one able to determine of their plaints and ſuites, nor place ſpatious enough to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115614:6"/>hear the ſuitors: then according to <hi>Jethroes</hi> counſell to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction or charge of Adminiſtring Juſtice was divided among very many, and ſeverall places aſſigned for that eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall purpoſe, that the people, as from ſo many Conduit-pipes, the <hi>aquam vitae</hi> the Law, that fountaine wherein the life and liberty of the people is conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, might receive.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Iſraelites, that were the firſt people to whom any written law was given, were wont to pronounce their Iudgments in the gate of every Citie, that the plainneſſe and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of their proceedings might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare; ſo that none might need to go out of the right way to ſeek for Iuſtice, and of purpoſe to ſhew, that Iudgment was a divine thing; then afterwards in <hi>Curia &amp; Foro</hi> the Athemians alſo in their temple called (by reaſon of a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Iudgment) <hi>Areopagus,</hi> and in the place called <hi>Palladium et Pritaneum:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit that the Caules, our neighbours (now called French-men) did hold their Aſſemblies for juſtice, only at <hi>Charnute</hi> and <hi>Charters,</hi> a place
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115614:7"/>ſcituate in the midſt of their Country that all the people might have indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reſort; after which order alſo the Brittons of this Iland did make their meetings, as it may well be gathered out of <hi>Caeſars Commentaries,</hi> where he plainly writeth, that theſe <hi>Druides</hi> (which then were the Iudges amongſt the <hi>Galls</hi>) had fetched that their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of diſcipline out of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> where we now dwell; yet Nevertheles the Saxons our Anceſtors (which ſuceeded them in this country) they retained the manner of the old Germans their owne elders (who as <hi>Tacitus</hi> writs <hi>Jura per pagos vicoſque reddebant</hi>) and they made diſtribution of Iuſtice not in one towne or in the princes palace; but alſo ſundry other ſpeciall places within the country.</p>
            <p>And truly the <hi>Normans,</hi> that invaded the poſterty of the ſame Saxons here did not ſo much after the ſubſtance, as the name of this the Saxons order, which they found at their comming higher, for (in effect) they did but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the word Gemote (which in the Saxon tongue ſignified in <hi>aſſembly</hi> or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115614:7"/>meeting together, into the french word <hi>Court</hi> or <hi>Cour</hi> (for ſo it is alſo found written) being a term of the ſelf ſame force and ſignification.</p>
            <p>This court (or <hi>Cour</hi>) therefore is derived of the latin <hi>Curia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cooke Epiſt to his</hi> 4 <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</hi> Curia a cura qui a eſt locus ubi publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas curas gerebant, <hi>or</hi> Curia <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>from the Lord, and ſo it is the Ks. Court or</hi> Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> which alſo is fetched from <hi>Cura,</hi> (as <hi>Valla</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) whereby is notified, that heed and care ought to be taken in the deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Controverſies: it ſignifieth properly both the aſſembly of men for the hearing of cauſes in variance, and the place alſo where that aſſembly is made; According to the firſt of which ſignifications, the Saxons as I ſaid, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it Gemote a meeting, of <hi>Gemettan,</hi> to meet, and agreeably to the ſecond, the kings houſe was firſt called a Court, becauſe the cheife Court of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice was holden there.</p>
            <p>But now of Courts ſome were called eccleſiaſtical, ſome Lay, and other ſome mixed (that is to ſay) both eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall and Lay.</p>
            <p>Of this laſt ſort I find but one name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the high Court of Parliament, which I call mixed, becauſe it had the Biſhops ioyned with the lay Lords to make up
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115614:8"/>the ſecond eſtate thereof, the firſt eſtate conſiſting of the Prince alone, and the third of the Commonalty, without any of the Clergy at all.</p>
            <p>Of which Court, albeit it was rather ſommoned to deviſe and create, reforme and repeale laws, than to put them in execution: yet foraſmuch as it both miniſtred the matter whereupon all the other Courts do work, and had in ſome cauſes ordinary juriſdictions alſo, I will ſpeake firſt, and then perſue my diviſion.</p>
            <p>That which wee now (agreeing with the Scotts and Iriſh) do call a Parliament, the Frenchmen do call <hi>Les Eſtates</hi> or <hi>aſſemble de les eſtates,</hi> becauſe with them there (as with as alſo) the King, Nobilitie and Commons (which be the three Eſtates of the land) do meet thereat to conſult: and the ſame in Germany is termed a Dyet: for theſe other Courts that carry the name of Parliament in France, be but ordinary Courts of Iuſtice which as (<hi>Paulus Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> writeth) are thought to have been planted by us, (and of which our own Councels eſtabliſhed in <hi>Wales,</hi> and in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115614:8"/>North parts do beare the neareſt ſhew and reſemblance.)</p>
            <p>This word Parliament (ſaith one) is Compounded of <hi>parium</hi> and <hi>lamentum,</hi> becauſe (as he thinketh) Peeres of the country did at thoſe meetings lament and complain each to other of the enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myties of their country, and thereupon provided redreſs for the ſame, but this is not very credible.</p>
            <p>But their opinion is more probable (as I think) which derive the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſimply from the French word Parler, and that alſo from the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> both ſignifying toſpeake, and ſo by adding the termination, <hi>mem</hi> (which is common in the french tongue, as well to many nounes, as adverbs) do make up Parliament, meaning thereby an Aſſembly of men called together to ſpeake, or confer of their advice and opinion, and ſo alſo it may not unfitly be called Parliament for that every man there doth or ſhould ſpeake his mind: but <hi>Laur. Valla</hi> miſliketh that kind of Etymologie,<note place="margin">Cooks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtit. fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 110. ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 164.</note> yet my Lord Cooke ſaith that it comes from <hi>parler lament,</hi> to ſpeake ones mind
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115614:9"/>and his authority is not mean.</p>
            <p>I will not take upon me to ſet downe the very time,<note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the word Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> in which the word Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament came firſt in uſe, but foraſmuch as it was tranſported out of <hi>France,</hi> it is not unprobable to gueſſe that it began here ſhortly after the time of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Conqueſt, One of the moſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique reports,<note place="margin">The name Parliament was uſed before the conquest in the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> the Confeſſor, <hi>Cooke 1</hi> Inſtit. ſect. <hi>164</hi> page <hi>110</hi>
               </note> that I think can be ſound of that name Parliament, is in the ſtatute made 3. E. 1. and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called—where that aſſembly is ſaid to be <hi>le Primer</hi> Parliament generall, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres coronement le Roy</hi> but yet that is not the very firſt uſe of the word, for in the ſtatute called <hi>Articuli clori</hi> and publiſhed 9. E. 2. theſe words are read amongſt others, <hi>Tempore progenitorum noſtrornm, quondam regum Angliae in diverſis Parliament is ſu is, &amp;c.</hi> which word <hi>progenitorum</hi> and <hi>quondam regum</hi> muſt needs reach higher than to E. 1. that was but father to him that ſpake it.</p>
            <p>So that I can willingly herein ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the opinion of <hi>Polydore Virgill</hi> who in the eleaventh book of his Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh hiſtory which contayneth the raigne of King Henry the firſt, that was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115614:9"/>ſon to the Conqu. writing of the great aſſembly at <hi>Saliſbury,</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>at illud appoſite habeo dicere reges ante haec tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora non conſueuiſſe populis conventum conſultandi cauſa, niſi perraro facere, adeo ut ab Hemico id inſtitutum jure manaſſe dici poſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</hi> and a little after, <hi>more galico vulgo Parliamentum appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant &amp;c.</hi> and this is ſo much the more credible, as that King laboured by all meanes, and eſpecially by reſtitution of the antient, lawes, (as all hiſtories do agree) to heale the hearts of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men, which were before deeply wounded by the oppreſſions of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and brother <hi>William,</hi> to the end that he might thereby the better keep the Crowne, of this Realme againſt his elder brother <hi>Rob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Witenage Mote Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noth, <hi>and</hi> Michell Gemote, <hi>names, of Parliament before the Conqueſt.</hi> Cook <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlit. fol.</hi> 110</note> who both had good right, and had moved his claim there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: but what time ſoever this Court be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be called by the name of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, this is certaine, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the ſame was before known to the Saxons (or Engliſh men) ſome times by the word <hi>Sinoth</hi> and <hi>Micell Sinoth,</hi> of the Greeke <hi>Synodos</hi> (now appropriated to eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall meetings only, and ſomtimes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115614:10"/>by theſe tearmes, <hi>micel-zemoce wizena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zemoze</hi> and <hi>aupa-picena zemoze,</hi> (that is to ſay) the great meeting, the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all the wiſe men, for <hi>wizan</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a wiſe man, and <hi>Gemote,</hi> a meeting: of which laſt word the names <hi>Shiyremoote, folemoote,</hi> and <hi>halymoote</hi> (that is to ſay) the aſſembly or meeting of men of a Shire of the men of a Towne and of the tenants of a Hall (or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor) had their beginnings alſo. And as <hi>Synoth</hi> is more uſed in the acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament themſelves, ſo <hi>Gemote</hi> is more familiar to the hiſtories: thus much as well of the preſent as of the antient uſuall name, now let us looke, into the thing it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Like as in warr where the King is preſent in perſon,<note place="margin">The confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and the reaſon of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates in Parliament</note> and with him the Nobilitie, Gentry, and Yeomonry, there is the force and puiſſance of the Realme: even ſo in peace, whereſoever is the prince (as the head) to give life (that is to ſay, yield the higheſt and the laſt aſſent, and where the Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie conſiſtting of the Lords ſpirituall and temporall, and the Commonalty made up of the Knights and Burgeſſes)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115614:10"/>be (as the body) preſent at his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, to deliberate, conferre, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult and conſent, there is alſo the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill and policie of the Realme, ſo that foraſmuch as every man, (from the higheſt to the loweſt) is there either in perſon or by procuration, therefore of right every man is ſaid to be bound by that law vvhich doth paſſe from ſuch an aſſembly.</p>
            <p>And this frame of policie, is both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and Harmonicall: 1. Naturall, in that it hath an imitation of the naturall body of man, truly called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a little vvorld, out of the 3 cells vvhereof, namely, the <hi>head, breaſt</hi> and <hi>belly,</hi> the vvhole three povvers of the ſoule do open and utter themſelves:</p>
            <p n="2">2 Harmonicall, becauſe from ſuch and ſo tuned a Baſe, Meane, and Treble;<note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Parliament</note> there proceedeth a moſt exquiſite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and delicious melody, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vvhich manner of conſultation,<note place="margin">Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den long before the Conqueſt. <hi>Mirror</hi> c. <hi>8</hi> ſect <hi>2</hi>
               </note> and namely, vvith us of this Realme I ſee not hovv I can derive it from any other time then from that in vvhich the Germans or Engliſh nation did ſet their firſt foot on this land to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115614:11"/>vade it, for <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> vvriteth thus <hi>nec regibus infinita poteſtas, de mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus rebus principes conſultant, de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioribus omnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither did they (together vvith the change of the ſoile) make change of this their vvonted manner of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration: for it is yet extant in monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments left behind them,<note place="margin">The con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment untill the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</note> that after their coming hither, they frequented the ſame order in counſelling vvhich they had uſed in their ovvne countrey be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Theſe two Kings are great exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plars of grave wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and would not truſt their own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tter of ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, but conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their wiſemen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it knowing that <hi>plus vident o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi quam oculus.</hi>
               </note> for proofe vvhereof I might call <hi>Beda</hi> the Saxon hiſtoriographer to vvittneſſe, vvho (reporting that the Chriſtian faith tooke roote by little and little amongſt them in their particular Kingdomes vvithin this land) vvriteth that King <hi>Edwyne</hi> of <hi>Northumberland</hi> vvould not embrace the preaching of the Goſpell before he had <hi>communed and conſulted with his freinds and Nobility,</hi> and Wiſemen, and that <hi>Sigeberth</hi> the King of <hi>Eaſtſex,</hi> being likevviſe moved to be baptized, did firſt call a <hi>Councell of his ſubiects,</hi> and finding them all to favour the motion, did then himſelfe alſo aſſent unto it.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115614:11"/>
            <p>But becauſe the Synodes (or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) themſelves be moſt faithfull witneſſes of their owne doings, and for that alſo the kingdome of the <hi>weſt ſax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> prevailing over the reſt, and meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it were) all their crownes to make on for hereſelfe, did in the end be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come miſtreſſe (or Monarch) of the whole <hi>Heptarchie</hi> (or ſeven King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms) into which this Land was firſt divided, I will for a while leave hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, and come to the Synodes, firſt ſhewing by one or two examples, what perſons were wont to be preſent at the parliament of that kingdome, and then confirming the like to have been uſed, after ſuch time as the whole land was reduced to one entire eſtate and monarchie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ine</hi> the King of <hi>Weſtſex</hi> who began his reign, about the year of the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our Lord Chriſt 712. begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Parliament thus: I Ine <hi>by Gods guift King of the weſt Saxons, with the advice and teaching of</hi> Cenred <hi>my father,</hi> Ireledde <hi>my Biſhop, and</hi> Ercenwold <hi>my Biſhop, and with all mine</hi> Aldermen <hi>and</hi> eldeſt wiſemen <hi>of my people, and alſo</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115614:12"/>a great aſſembly of Gods ſervants <hi>was carefull concerning the health of our ſoules, and the eſtabliſhment of our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp;c.</hi> Now let us ſee if three eſtates of Parliament (that is to ſay) the King, the Nobilitie, and Commons, may beſound here.</p>
            <p>Firſt the Kings name is expreſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Noblitie is ſignified under theſe Biſhops and Aldermen; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the diviſion of the Realme into Shires, every large Territorie had an Alderman or governor: who was after the allotment into ſhires for the moſt part an Earle, in token whereof all our Earles to this day do beare the name of one ſhire or other.</p>
            <p>The Commonalty is partly included in the words: <hi>the Eldeſt wiſemen of my people,</hi> which betoken the laytie, and partly in the words, A <hi>great aſſemblie of Gods ſervants</hi> vvhich do notifie the Clergie ſo called then, as it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the firſt Chapter of the very ſame lavves, for that they vvere conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to Gods ſervice. And leſt any man ſhould thinke that theſe eſtates vvere called together more for their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115614:12"/>advice and counſell, to be given to the king, then for any authority (or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt) that they had in making the lavve, the preamble calleth thoſe lavves, <hi>our dooms, or Iudgments.</hi> And the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veivv ſaith, <hi>wee bid or command,</hi> in the plurall number, vvhich alſo may not be reſtrained to the King only for honour ſake, as vvee novv uſe to ſpeake, for he is there named <hi>I Ine,</hi> in the ſingular only: Thus much I note once for all. That I be not hereafter troubled to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the ſame thing often.</p>
            <p>About one hundred yeares after the death of this <hi>Ine,</hi> one <hi>Aldred</hi> a King of the vveſt Saxons alſo, as he calleth himſelfe, but rather King of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men and Saxons (as <hi>Aſſerius</hi> ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that vvrote his life) did as he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in his preface to his lavves, gather together and put in vvriting certain ordinances made by vviſe men in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Synods of ſundry former Kings: as namely <hi>Ine</hi> aforeſaid, <hi>Offa</hi> King of mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle England, and <hi>Ethelbert</hi> of Kent, the <hi>firſt chriſtned Prince</hi> of all the Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nation; vvhich collection of lavves he alſo ſaieth that he ſhevved to all his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115614:13"/>vviſe men, and they alſo thought them meet to be obſerved, but what maketh it to the three eſtates (will ſome man ſay) that the kings and their wiſemen (which may well ſeem to be but their privy Counſellors) did eſtabliſh lawes. yes very much: for here the word <hi>Witena.</hi> (wiſemen) doth include the Nobilitie and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons becauſe they be Counſellors of the Realme for the time in reſpect whereof the aſſemblie of them was of ſome, called <hi>Witena Gemote</hi> a meeting of the wiſemen as I told you, And of other it is termed <hi>Commune conſilium Regni,</hi> the comon counſell of the Realme, and that this muſt be ſo underſtood in this place, I will uſe none other argument, then the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of <hi>Alfred</hi> himſelfe drawne out of the ſame place; for he ſaith (as you have heard) that the lawes of the King <hi>Ine</hi> were made by a Synode of wiſemen, and what thoſe wiſemen were, you here alſo underſtand by the report of King <hi>Ine</hi> himſelfe And the ſtile of his owne lawes (that is to ſay) by the Nobilitie and Comunalty beſides the King.</p>
            <p>Furthermore that I loſe not another
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115614:13"/>advantage offered me by this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, I muſt alſo gather hereby, That not only the Kings of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland, Eſſex,</hi> and <hi>Weſtſex</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the three eſtates in making their Lawes, but alſo that they of <hi>Kent,</hi> and <hi>middle England,</hi> maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſame order: for King <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freds</hi> words (as you ſee) are one and the ſame for them all, and then conſequently their manner was one and the ſame through all.</p>
            <p>But now that I may at the length leave theſe <hi>heptarchies</hi> or petie Kings, and paſſe to the <hi>Monarchies</hi> and great ones, the ſame <hi>Alfred</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the whole nation had yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves unto him, and were ſhrowded under his protection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the furious ſtorm of the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh invaſion, did at one time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a peace with <hi>Guthrum</hi> the King of the <hi>Danes,</hi> the ſtile where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of beginneth thus: <hi>This is the peace that King Alfred and King Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrum and all the wiſemen of the Engliſh nation have taken &amp;c.</hi> Loe here you ſee (<hi>Ealra Witena Gemote</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115614:14"/>an aſſemblie of all the wiſemen) After him, <hi>Edward</hi> called his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to <hi>Exceſter,</hi> and conſulted with them for the better obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the peace of his own Realm, And he alſo at another time by the adviſe of his wiſemen renued and confirmed the league that <hi>Alfred</hi> had before taken with the Daniſh Captain.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Ethelſtane</hi> concludeth his famous Parliament holden at <hi>Grateley</hi> thus: All this was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in that great Synod at <hi>Grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> at the which was the Arch-Biſhop <hi>Walfhelme</hi> with all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen and Wiſemen, that King <hi>Ethelſtane</hi> gathered together, and the ſame King did alſo afterward call another aſſemblie of his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to Exceſter to conſult for the better execution of thoſe former Ordinances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edmond</hi> the King ſummoned a great Synod at <hi>London</hi> both of the order of the Spiritualty and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralty, the which (in the ſecond part of the Law there made)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115614:14"/>he called by a generall name, his <hi>(Witena)</hi> wiſemen, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them all for their help in that advice.</p>
            <p>And after him King <hi>Edgar</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed certaine lawes which were made (as he ſaith) by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of his wiſemen.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>K. Edgar made lawes</hi> frequenti ſenatu, <hi>he began to raign,</hi> 959. Lambard. <hi>f.</hi> 62. Etheldred <hi>had</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium <hi>and be began to raign</hi> 979. Lam. <hi>f.</hi> 88.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The like title and concluſion have thoſe ſtatutes alſo which King <hi>Etheldred</hi> ordained at <hi>Woodſtock</hi> and the league which he made with <hi>Anlaf,</hi> another of the Captaines of the Daniſh armie, is intituled to be made by him and his wiſemen.</p>
            <p>And certain other acts there be (though hitherto not imprinted) of a Parliament that was aſſembled in the yeare of Chiſt 1008. which fell under the raign of the ſame King, which are there reported to have paſſed under the <hi>authority of the King and his wiſemen,</hi> both ſpirituall and lay, in which ſaid laſt ordinances, this one thing for this purpoſe is worthy of obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: That whereas in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the lawes all the acts are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115614:15"/>ſaid to paſſe from the King and his wiſemen both of the Clergie and Laytie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>It is alſo ſuppoſed that the</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultum de monticolis Walliae, <hi>was in this Kings time, the title is</hi> Conſultum quod An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes &amp; Walliae conſiliarij de monti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colis fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Lamb. 94.</note> in all the body and proceſſe of the law each ſtatute ſaith thus: <hi>And it is the advice of our Lord and his Wiſemen</hi> ſo (as it ſeemeth plainly) that it was then a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſpeech, to ſignifie both the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualty and Laity that is to ſay the Nobility and Comons, by the onely word, <hi>Witena.</hi> (or Wiſemen.)</p>
            <p>Finally thoſe lawes of the great King and Monarch <hi>Canute</hi> or <hi>(Knoate)</hi> which he made at <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> and be yet remaining, do beare face and teſtimonie that they were made by him and his <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Se of this</hi> Guliel. Lamb. 97.</note> And there is an antient writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten treatiſe intituled <hi>Modus tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di parliamentum tempore regis Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardi filii Etheldredi</hi> to be ſeen in many hands, purportng the very order, forme: and manner of all this ſtately Court and Aſſemblie.</p>
            <p>Now as theſe written authorities do undoubtedly confirm our aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the continuance of this manner of Parliament, ſo is there
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115614:15"/>alſo unwritten law (or preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that doth no leſſe infallibly uphold the ſame: for it is well known that in every quarter of the Realm a great many <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> do yet ſend Burgeſſes to the Parliament, which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe be ſo antiently, and ſo long ſince decayed and gone to naught, that it cannot be ſhewed that they have been of any reputation at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time ſince the Conqueſt, and much leſſe they have obtained that priveledge by the Grant of the King ſucceeding the ſame; ſo that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt they have in Parliament groweth by an ancient uſage before the Conqueſt, whereof they cannot ſhew any beginning which thing alſo is confirmed by a contrary uſage in the ſelfeſame thing: for it is likewiſe known, that they of <hi>ancient demeaſne</hi> do preſcribe in not ſending to the Parliament, for which reaſon alſo they are neither contributaries to the wages of the Knights there, neither are they bound by ſundry Acts of Parliament
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115614:16"/>though the ſame be generally penned and do make no exception of them.</p>
            <p>But there is no ancient Demeaſne ſaving that only which is deſcribed in the book of <hi>Domeſday</hi> under the title of <hi>Terra Regis,</hi> which of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie muſt be ſuch as either was in the hands of the <hi>Conquerour</hi> himſelfe (who made that booke) or of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor that was before him.</p>
            <p>And ſo again if they of ancient demeaſne have ever ſince the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,<note place="margin">Mirror, c. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> preſcribed not to ſend Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes to the Parliament, then (no doubt) there was a Parliament before the Conqueſt, to the which they of other places did ſend their Burgeſſes; which ſeeing it is ſo, let us come neerer and examine whether the ſame order have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſince that time or no.<note place="margin">The conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of Parliament after the Conqueſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To looke for a Parliament (aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled of the Engliſh nation and Commons) ſoon after the Conqueſt were but to labour without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of good ſpeed; for <hi>Silent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115614:16"/>leges inter arma.</hi>
               <note place="margin">There were in the time of, and ſince the conqueſt in the raigns of H <hi>1.</hi> K. Stephen H. <hi>2.</hi> R. <hi>1.</hi> K. John H. <hi>3.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>280.</hi> Parliaments and acts made at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſeſſion <hi>Cook 1.</hi> Jnſt ſect. <hi>164.</hi> p. <hi>110.</hi> See <hi>Polyd. l. 11.</hi> and <hi>Hollingſh,</hi> p. <hi>354.</hi> of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments in England.</note> And during all the raign of the Conquerour either the ſword was not put up into the ſcabbard, or if it were, the hand was alwayes upon the hilt ready to draw it again.</p>
            <p>So unwilling on the one part were the Engliſh men to take the yoak, and more that rather their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was to be compell'd, then their opinions to be conſulted, and ſo haughty on the other part were the Normans victors, that to be called an Engliſh-man was in their eye a great contumelie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
            <p>His ſon <hi>William</hi> alſo did rather pretend in word, ſome releaſe of the former auſterity in government than perform it in deed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience: But his other ſon (the firſt <hi>Henry</hi> that ever raigned here) did not only at his Coronation promiſe reſtitution of St. <hi>Edwards</hi> laws (as we call them) but alſo delivered out his free Charter of the Grant of the ſame; in which (as <hi>M. Paris</hi> reporteth he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115614:17"/>that he was crowned by the Common-Councell of the Barons of the Realme of <hi>England</hi> and there it may happily ſeeme ſtrange to affirm that this was a full Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in the which there is no other mention but of theſe Barons only: But if it be conſidered, firſt, that the Germans expound and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the word <hi>Baro,</hi> by Freehears, a freeman, then that <hi>Math. Paris</hi> ſaith that the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> were at that time called <hi>Barons:</hi> And alſo that even yet Burgeſſes of the Five Ports do paſſe under the ſame name of Barons, and that every man (almoſt) hath his Court-Baron; It ſhall not be altogether without ground, to ſay that both the Nobility and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty of the Realme were meant under theſe words <hi>(the Barons of the Realm)</hi> the rather becauſe that ſpeech is accompanied with the words (Common-Councell) and for that alſo, the ſelfe ſame Author doth afterward uſe the words <hi>Comunis aſſenſus Baronagii</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115614:17"/>when he intendeth to ſignifie a juſt Parliament <hi>Ingulphus</hi> who died before 1109. ſaith <hi>Rex Eldredus convocavit magnates, Epiſcopos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceres &amp; optimates ad tractandum de publ. negotiis Regni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit ſince I labour not with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny penurie of proof, I wil relinquiſh the advantage of this matter, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring only that they may be called to memorie which <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> hath before acknowledged concerning the reſtitution of the form of the Parliament made by this very ſame King, of whom alſo the <hi>Saxon Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles</hi> of <hi>Peterborough Abby</hi> do teſtifie, that in the yeare after Chriſt 1123. he ſent his writers over all <hi>England,</hi> and bad his <hi>Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Abbots,</hi> and all his <hi>Theignes</hi> (which ſignifie aſmuch as Barons before) that they ſhould come to his <hi>Witena Gemote,</hi> on <hi>Candlemas day</hi> to <hi>Gloceſter</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to leave him, and to leap o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Stephen,</hi> becauſe he hath ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven longer for the Crown then he enjoyed it. King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115614:18"/>(ſaith <hi>Mathew Paris</hi>) in the year of our Lord Chriſt, 1185. <hi>Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavit Clericos Regni, &amp; populum cum omni nobilitate apud fontem Clericorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet again to paſſe over his two ſons, <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> whereof the one ſpent the moſt part of his Raign in battell abroad, and the other in Civill warrs at home. I read in the ſame Author, that King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, did in the year of our Lord, 1225. call together <hi>Omnes Clericos &amp; laicos totius regni;</hi> Which aſſembly the ſame writer alſo in ſome places ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth by the words <hi>Vniverſitas regni,</hi> but what need I to hang long on the credit of Hiſtorians, ſeeing from this time downward the authentique writers of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments themſelves do offer mee preſent help.</p>
            <p>The great Charter of <hi>England</hi> (which paſſed from this King about this time, and for which the Engliſh men had no leſſe ſtriven
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115614:18"/>than the Trojans for their <hi>Helena</hi>) beareth no ſhew of an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and yet I will prove by the Depoſitions of two ſundry Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, That it was made by the comon aſſent of all the Realme in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, for ſo ſaith the ſtatute called <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio Chartae. Anno.</hi> 25. E. 1. in flat Termes, and the ſtatute made at <hi>Weſtminſter Anno.</hi> 25. E. 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. ſaith, that it was made by the King, Peeres and Commons of the land: in the 20. year of the ſame King <hi>Henry,</hi> the ſtatute of <hi>Mert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> was publiſhed, which ſaith thus. <hi>Proviſum fuit &amp; conſeſſum tam a praedictis Archiepiſcopis Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis, Comitibus, Baronibus quam ab ipſo rege &amp; aliis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the 52. yeare of his raign was the ſtatute of <hi>Marle-bridge</hi> made, <hi>provideat</hi> (as it ſelf ſpeaketh) <hi>ipſo domino rege ac con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocatis diſcetioribus eiuſdem Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni tam majoribus quam minoribus proviſum eſt &amp;. ſtatutum. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115614:19"/>
            <p>The ſtatute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the firſt, which was made in the third yeare of E. 1. hath this title. <hi>The eſtabliſhments of King Edward made by this Councell and by the Aſſent of the Archbiſhops, Biſhops Abbots, Earles, Barons and all the Comonalty of the land thither ſumo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> The ſtatute made at <hi>Glouceſter</hi> in the 6. year of the ſame Kings raign is there ſaid to be thus made. <hi>Purrelant le Roy &amp; apelles le pluis diſcretes de ſon Royalme auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bien des greinders come des meindres eſtablie eſt &amp; concordantment orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To draw to an end, King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond held a Parliament in the 14. year of his raign wherein are theſe words. <hi>Le (Roy per aſſent des Prelates, Counts, Barons, &amp; tout le Comunaltie de ſon Realme en le Parliament &amp;c.</hi> and the like ſpeech hath he in another ſtatute that he made. <hi>Ne quis occaſionetur pro morte Petri de Gaveſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not think that I ſhall need
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115614:19"/>to ſpeake for further proofes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Records of Parliaments after this time: for they do from henceforth not only ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſuch ſtore and plenty, but alſo ſet forth the ſeverall ſtates themſelves, the duty of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the paines of their default or departure, and ſundry other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances ſo particularly and plainly, that as I might well be charged (if you would ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them) in a matter not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to have uſed ſpeech nothing at all needfull: and yet leaſt any man ſhould ſuſpect, that any of the two eſtates of this Aſſemblie deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his voice in Parliament from the authority of any of theſe later lawes, I muſt leave him to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that in one ſhort Statute of Parliament (holden in the 5, year of King <hi>Richard</hi> 2. ſtatute 2. ca. 4. he may reade it 4. ſeverall times plainly ſpoken, that this was done anciently and of <hi>old time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that here again alſo Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115614:20"/>is ready to ſerve the turne, and to ſay the truth, this one law may ſtand for an Interpreter of all the reſt, for whether they be ſaid to be made by the King and his Barons, or by the King and his Clergie and Laytie, or by the King and his diſcreeter men, both great and ſmall, or by the common. Aſſent of all the Realme, as I have already ſhewed, or by the King and his Wiſemen, or by the King and his Councell, or his Comon-Councell, or by the King, Earles, Barons and other Wiſemen, or after ſuch other like phraſes whereof you may meet with many in the volumes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; it cometh all to this one point, namely that <hi>the King his Nobilitie and Commons did ordaine them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (which is more) if you ſhall find any act of Parliament ſeeming to paſſe under the name and authoritie of the King only (as ſome have that <hi>ſhew</hi> indeed) yet you muſt not by and by judge that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115614:20"/>it was eſtabliſhed without the Aſſent of the other eſtates.</p>
            <p>To take one example for the reſt, The ſtatute of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> (made the 6. <hi>E.</hi> 1.) ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Our ſoveraigne Lord the King, for the amendment of the land, hath provided the ſtatutes under-written &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet the ſtatutes made at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (in the 13, year of that King) and the ſtatute of <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> (ſet forth in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. year of that King alſo) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eciting that ſtatute of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> do plainly acknowledge; the one, that it was provided by the more diſcreet men of the Realme, aſwell of the high as of the low degree being called together; and the other, that it was made by the King, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling together the Earles, Prelates, Barons, and his Councell, And therefore it was well noted by Judge <hi>Brook,</hi> That though <hi>magna Charta,</hi> and ſundry other old ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes do run in the name of the Prince
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115614:21"/>only, yet the other eſtates are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in all good underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Againe whether the forme of an Act be thus. The King with the Aſſents of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons doth eſtabliſh, or thus: It is enacted at the requeſt of the Lords and Commons whereto the King aſſenteth, or thus: by the Aſſent of the King, and of the Lords ſpirituall and Temporall, and of the Commons it is enacted, or thus: It is enacted by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this preſent Parliament; It is alſo all one in effect and ſubſtance: for the words (<hi>aſſenteth</hi> and <hi>enacteth</hi>) are <hi>equivalent</hi> in this caſe,<note place="margin">7. <hi>H.</hi> 7.14. &amp; 2 <hi>H.</hi> 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> as it is holden 7. <hi>H.</hi> 7.14. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 2. <hi>H.</hi> 7.27. whereas otherwiſe the neceſſitie of the Aſſent of all the 3. eſtates of Parliament is ſuch, as without any one of them the reſt will loſe their labour: For it fell out upon a time, that the King in Parliament willed that a certain man ſhould be attainted, and ſhould loſe his hands, whereunto the Lords
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115614:21"/>aſſented. But becauſe there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſpoken of the Commons, it was adjudged by all the Iuſtices (4. <hi>H.</hi> 7.18.) That this was no Acte that might binde,<note place="margin">4. <hi>H.</hi> 7.18.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the partie was reſtored.</p>
            <p>Hitherto of the Continuance and Aſſent of this our firſt and higheſt Court,<note place="margin">This Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogateth, repealeth, and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth Lawes ſtatutes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> concerning matters ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, capitall, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, civill, martiall, maritine, <hi>&amp;c. Cook. 1: Inſt fol. 110. ſect. 164.</hi> ſee <hi>4. Inſt. chap. Parlia. ment.</hi>
               </note> whereunto after that I ſhall have added a word or two of the juriſdiction thereof, I will proceed to the reſt, if all judgements (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid) be converſant either in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of offences, or in the deciſion of controverſies, then is the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Parliament of as ample authority as the aſſent of any or all other Courts whatſoever: for it declareth the lawes that do bind all perſons in all Cauſes aſwell eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall as temporall, whereof you may ſee a great many examples in the volume of the old ſaxon Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, how ſtrange a thing ſo ever the popiſh Clergie in former times have thought it to be, it hath juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115614:22"/>alſo in ſuch cauſes which have need of help, and for which there is no help by any law alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in force. And whereon the erronious Judgments of any other Courts muſt be reverſed by a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er authority, this Court doth not only reverſe the errors of the upper Bench, formerly called the Kings Bench, which is ſuperior to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but it may alſo amend the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors committed by the Parliament it ſelf, if any ſuch ſhall at any time appeare.</p>
            <p>Eccleſiaſticall Courts were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in number, &amp; diverſe in nature, whereof the Chiefe was the <hi>Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of the Clergie of the whole nation of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> which was aſſembled together with the eſtates of Parliament, and it conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of the Deanes, Chapters, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, Procurators of all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Churches, the next were the 2. <hi>provinciall Synods</hi> of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> and of <hi>Yorke,</hi> to the later of the which, there were only three
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115614:22"/>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks ſubject, that is to ſay, <hi>Durham, Carliſle,</hi> and <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and all the reſt owed their obedience to the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After thoſe were the generall Courts of the Arch-Biſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (that is to ſay) the <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> (or Court) of the <hi>Arches</hi> for Appellations, the Court of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> (of the Chancellours Court) which was wont to be in the Arch-Biſhops houſe; The <hi>Commiſſaries</hi> (or the Praerogative) Court (which is now in being) for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of Teſtaments, and the Court of <hi>Faculties</hi> for diſpenſations; then followed the ſpeciall Courts of this Arch-Biſhop, namely his <hi>Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> holden by his Commiſſary at <hi>Canterbury</hi> for his diocaeſſe, and laſtly the Court of thoſe <hi>peculiar Deanaries</hi> which did belong unto him, and do ly in the diocaeſſes of other Biſhopps; The other Arch-Biſhops (and each other Biſhop) had in his owne Dioceſſe the Court of his <hi>Chancellour,</hi> and the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115614:23"/>Court of his Archdeacon or his Officiall.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as the deſcription of theſe eccleſiaſticall Courts, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth to another learning, (I meane to the Civill and Canon Laws by which they were gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) and do withall require a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treatiſe by themſelves, I will content my ſelf with this bare enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration of them at this time, and bend my labour to the diſcovery of the Lay (or temporall) Courts that now have place amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Lay Courts were of two ſorts,<note place="margin">The ſorts of Lay Courts in antient time.</note> at the firſt only <hi>baſe,</hi> and <hi>high;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the beginning whereof, I read that even as <hi>Moſes</hi> (the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall miniſter of Juſtice appointed by God) finding himſelf unable to ſuſtain the burden of deciding all the Controverſies of the people,<note place="margin">Deut. 1. Exod. 18.</note> did ſet Judges <hi>over Tribes, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds Fifties, and Tenths</hi> of the multitude, to whom he referred the determination of <hi>ſmaller</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, reſerving to himſelf the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115614:23"/>of matters that were of <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> importance; ſo alſo that Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (but Chriſtian King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) <hi>Alfred,</hi> divided his whole Realm of <hi>England</hi> firſt into <hi>Shires,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diviſion of the Realm for juriſ. diction.</note> then thoſe ſhires into <hi>Rathes, Rapes,</hi> or <hi>Rideings,</hi> and theſe again into <hi>Wapentakes</hi> or <hi>Hundreds;</hi> and laſtly, thoſe alſo into <hi>Leets, Barons,</hi> or <hi>Tything,</hi> and did withall eſtabliſh juriſdiction in every of theſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the Reeves or Judges of the lower roomes, authority of hearing <hi>ſmaller</hi> ſuites, granting <hi>greater</hi> power to the Shiriffs and Aldermen, which have charge of greater Aſſemblyes, and detaining to himſelf the deciſion of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as by juſt cauſe of appellation, (either for Law or equity,) ſhould be brought unto him.</p>
            <p>This Court of the whole Shire was of two ſorts, whereof the one then called <hi>Scyre-Gemote,</hi> that is the Aſſembly of the Shire, and now termed the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> turn, was then (as now alſo) holden twice in one
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115614:24"/>year: And this Court was of like juriſdiction, to the Court of the <hi>Leet,</hi> or of the Boroughs or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as it was then called: The ſecond and the Hundred Court (then named <hi>Hundre deſ-Gemote</hi>) was in thoſe appointed to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den once in a month at the leaſt, and that was of like nature to the <hi>County Court</hi> (which is now kept every month alſo) unto the Court Baron antiently called <hi>healgemote,</hi> and corruptly <hi>halymote,</hi> that is (as I ſaid) the Court of a Hall (or chief place) which is now at this day to be kept, and maintained once in three weeks, if the Lord will ſo have it.</p>
            <p>I read further more in the Laws of the Saxon King <hi>Edgar,</hi> thus: <hi>ne Geſece nan man Sone Synz &amp;c.</hi> Let no man ſeek to the King in matter of variance, unleſſ he cannot find right at home; but if that right be too heavy for him, then let him ſeek to the King to have it lightned.</p>
            <p>The very like whereof is to be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115614:24"/>ſeen (in effect in the Laws of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutus</hi> the <hi>Dane</hi> ſometimes King of this Nation alſo.<note place="margin">The hygh Court of juſtice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for Laws and equity.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Out of which laws I gather four things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that every man had means to uſe in theſe baſe Courts at home in the Countrey for the recovery of his right.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Then that no man ought to uſe it out of the County, or to draw his plea from thence without good cauſe, both which things lye plainly in the letter of this Law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the King himſelf hath a high Court of Juſtice where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſeemeth, that he ſate in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for the words be: Let him not ſeek the King.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, that the ſame Court of the King did judge, not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to meer right, and Law, but alſo after equity and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <p>For firſt the words be: unleſſe he cannot find right at home, by which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115614:25"/>it is permitted that then he might uſe to go to the King for right.</p>
            <p>Secondly Again, if that right be too heavy, then let him ſeek to the King <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby it is meant, that he ſhould have the <hi>rigor</hi> of the Law mitigated by the <hi>conſcience</hi> of the Prince, and after this order, and in theſe two ſorts of Courts was all Juſtice adminiſtred untill the time of King <hi>William the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> during whoſe reign (as allſo under the Government of King <hi>Rufus</hi> his ſon) it is to be thought, that the ordinary courſe of Juſtice was greatly diſturbed, as well by reaſon of the inteſtine and ſorraign wars, as alſo becauſe that theſe two Princes governed by a meer and abſolute power, as in a Realm ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned by <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> but yet it was ſo farre off, that any of them did ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aboliſh theſe Courts, That the ſame did not only remain du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all their times, (howſoever put to ſilence for the ſeaſon) but alſo had continuance afterwards,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115614:25"/>and do yet (as they may) here bear life amongſt us: for, as I ſaid, thoſe baſe Courts of the Shires, Hundreds, Boroughs, and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, do yet continue in manuer the ſame in ſubſtance that they then were, and that the pleas ought no more to be taken from then now in our dayes (without cauſe) then they ought to have been, may evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently be proved by the writs of <hi>Tolt, pone accedas. ad Curiam,</hi> and <hi>Recordari,</hi> vhich wee now yet uſe, and that to this only end, to remove ſuits upon cauſe out of one Court into another.</p>
            <p>The like I may alſo affirm of that high Court which then followed the King himſelf, for albeit that many particular high Courts be now ſince that time advanced, by reaſon that the multitude of ſuits (ſtill increaſing with the iniquity of the age of, the World,) would not ſuffer them all to be ordered in one place, without both into ler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble delay of matters, and grievous
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115614:26"/>vexation of men, yet nevertheleſs if ye will throughly behold the matter, and ſubject about which all theſe Courts are now occupied, you ſhall perceive that they are but as it were ſo many branches ſprung up out of that one tree or ſtream derived from the ſame ſpring and ſountaine.</p>
            <p>For letting paſs thoſe Courts of the Country which I have already touched, alſo thoſe other ſmall Courts of record that be in <hi>Cityes</hi> and <hi>Townes corporate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pipowders of Pies and powldres, that is duſty feet: becauſe it is for Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailers to the ſayr</note> yea, and the <hi>Pipowders</hi> Court it ſelf that laſteth no longer then the Fayr, All our higher Cours at this day be either Courts of right and Law, or elſe of <hi>equity and conſcience,</hi> as they then were, although they now require another ſubdiviſion, than they then had; And that (if you will) may be this.</p>
            <p>The Courts of Law do either handle civil or criminall cauſes:<note place="margin">The late diviſion of Lay Courts</note> And theſe Civill cauſes be either moved between the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115614:26"/>and the people of <hi>England</hi> (formerly between the King his tenants and ſubiects) or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween one ſubiect and another.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Courts of Law that hold plea of common or civill matters that grew between the Prince and ſubiects be theſe.</p>
            <p>The Exchequer deviſed for the ſafe cuſtody of the lands formerly called the Crowne lands, and for the faithfull anſwering of the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the ſame. The Court of wards and Liveryes, and the Court of the dutchy of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> both which are now altered.</p>
            <p>And the Chancery Court (at the leaſt) ſo far forth as the ſame hath to do with Petitions, traverſes —<hi>de droith</hi> and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Thoſe other Courts of Law that have juriſdiction of civil or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas ariſing between, ſubiect, and ſubiect, be theſe. The Common Place or Bench: The <hi>Marſhalſea</hi> for matters heretoſore within the vierge, or limits aſſigned to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115614:27"/>Kings houſe or Palace: The Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty Court, which was for marine Cauſes: And the <hi>upper Bench,</hi> in time paſt termed the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> ſo far forth as it yet doth retain juriſdiction in matters of debt, Aſſumptions, Actions upon the Caſe, and ſuch other things properly tryable in the Common Place, and not there.</p>
            <p>Criminall cauſes do generally belong to the upper Bench, and have formerly belonged to the Starre Chamber, or elſe particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do appertaine to the Conſtables Court, to the Marſhaſie, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty, Goale delivery, Oyer and Detorminer, and Seſſions of the Peace. And theſe be the Courts of Law that have ordinary reſort and juriſdiction. The Courts of Conſcience be theſe, Firſt the Chancery open to all men at all times. Secondly the Court of the <hi>Requeſt,</hi> that did hear only the ſuits of poor men, and of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſervants. Thirdly The <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115614:27"/>Court, that was within the Exchequer: and Fourthly, two <hi>Councills,</hi> which formerly were eſtabliſhed, the one in <hi>Wales,</hi> and the other in the <hi>North</hi> Country, both conſiſting of <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Councill,</hi> now taken away, which were like unto thoſe which in <hi>France</hi> are called Parliaments, as I ſaid before.</p>
            <p>But now to the end that it may the more evidently appear how, and by what degrees of increaſe, theſe many Courts have ſprung out of that one, it is requiſite that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede to the hiſtory of King, <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> the Conqueror (where I left) and to deſcend from him, down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, untill I have ſet all on foote.<note place="margin">The Court of Exchequer. The Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Court is of originall juriſdiction without any Commiſſion <hi>Cook: 4. Inſt. c. 11. p. 130.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>It is confeſſed by all writings that the Conqueror after ſuch time as he had ſuppreſſed the forces of thoſe that made head againſt him here, did immediatly cauſe the whole Realm to be exactly ſurvey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Shires,</hi> and <hi>Hundreds,</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally aſwell for the underſtanding
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115614:28"/>of the woods, paſtures, meadows, and tillage thereof,<note place="margin">The firſt ſurvey of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was by <hi>Alfred</hi> about <hi>872.</hi> the Regiſter thereof was kept in his treaſury at <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell f. 11.</hi>
               </note> as alſo of the profitts of Churches, Mills, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, and of all other Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties whatſoever. The record of which ſurvey was then called <hi>Domeſday Book,</hi> and was appoynted to be kept in the Exchequer at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where it now reſteth. And that Court did he then alſo newly erect for the ordering of his revenues, after the name of the Exchequer: in <hi>Normandie</hi> it had not only the government of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the Duke there, but was alſo the ſoveraigne Court for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of juſtice amongſt his ſubjects,<note place="margin">Cuſtom Normand. 48.52.635.</note> and ſo continued untill that <hi>Lewis</hi> (the 12. King of <hi>France</hi>) converted it into a Court of Parliament conſiſting of Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Counſellors, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it at <hi>Roan</hi> in <hi>Normandie,</hi> where it now remaineth: But this his Exchequer in <hi>England</hi> had only the direction of his demeaſns and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, the adminiſtration of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115614:28"/>juſtice continuing ſtill in that other Court of his as it was before his coming hither: For proofe of which matter I call to witneſſe <hi>Gervaſius Tilberienſis,</hi> a learned man that lived ſo neer to the time of the Conqueſt, that he confeſſeth he had talk with <hi>Henry</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> which was ſon to the Conquerours ſiſter.</p>
            <p>This man was an officer of the Exchequer, here, and penned ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dialogues of the obſervations of the Exchequer which he dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, and are yet in the Exchequer in the <hi>Black Booke</hi> there, in the firſt part of which his dialogues, ca. 1. he writeth (for the advancement of the Antiquity of the Exchequer) that it was brought out of <hi>Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> by the Conquerour; and for the authority of the Court he hath (amongſt other words) theſe following: <hi>Nulli licet ſtatuta Scac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carii infringere, vel eis quavis te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritate reſiſtere, habet enim hoc
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115614:29"/>commune, cum ipſa domini Regis curia, in qua ipſc in propria perſona jura decernit, quod nec recordationl, nec ſententiae in eo latae, liceat alieni contradicere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby it is plainly proved, the Court of the Exchequer was at that time a diſtinct Court from that Court of the King, in the which he himſelf ſometimes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly his juſtice (called then <hi>Prima juſtitia</hi>) did uſe to ſit.</p>
            <p>The one Court, having autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over the Kings demeaſns and receipts (as <hi>Gervaſius</hi> in all that worke at large diſcourſeth) and the other uſing the power of diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting common juſtice, as his words in this place do ſufficiently purport.</p>
            <p>And therefore I cannot (but here by the way) note the error of them, which do maintain, that the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer was (in this time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond) a Court of whatſoever Common pleas for all ſubjects, and which for proof of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115614:29"/>their aſſertion) do alledge the Title of Mr. <hi>Glanvil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>'s book in part thus: <hi>Et illas ſolum leges continet &amp; conſuetudines ſecundum quas placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur in curia Regis ad ſcaccarium,</hi> for overthrow whereof, firſt, I ſay, that the words of this title be not the words of <hi>Glanvill</hi> himſelf, but of that man (whatſoever he were) that publiſhed his book by print. for he entituleth the book thus, <hi>Tractatus de legibus &amp; tempore Reg is Henrici ſecundi compoſitus, illuſtri viro Ranulpho de Glanvill juris regni &amp; antiquarum Conſuctudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eo tempore peritiſſimo,</hi> which doth plainly diſcover, that he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of <hi>Glanvilla</hi> as of another man, and which alſo lived not then but at another time.</p>
            <p>Secondly I affirm, that if it were the ſpeech of <hi>Glanvill</hi> himſelf, yet (if you will take the reſt of his words with you) then you ſhall ſee that they have another meaning: for the words ſtand thus together, <hi>Secundum quas placitatur in Curia
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115614:30"/>Regis ad Saccarium &amp; coram Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis ubicunque fuerint:</hi> which words <hi>coram Juſticiis ubicunque fuerint</hi>) do ſet forth the other Courts of the King whereof I now ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I undertake to ſhew, not by the title, but by the Text of <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills</hi> owne booke, that in his time the Kings Court was one, and the Exchequer another: for through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his whole worke, he called the Court of Common P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eas <hi>Curiam Domine Regis,</hi> And the Stile of the writ therefore is, <hi>quod ſit coram me vel Juſticiis meis:</hi> But when he cometh to ſpeake of the Exchequer, he talketh of Acompts to be made to the King there, and of none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter: as namely in the 7. book <hi>Ca.</hi> 10. where he hath this, <hi>Si dominus Rex aliquam cuſtodiam alicui commiſerit tunc diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur utrum ei cuſtodiam pleno jure commiſerit, ita quod nullum inde reddere compotum oporteat ad Scae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arium, aut aliter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before that I leave the raign
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115614:30"/>of this King <hi>Henry the ſecond:</hi> I muſt add this alſo, that he in the xxiii. of his raign did (by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of ſome of his Biſhops) cut the Realm into 6. parts, and to every of theſe parts appointed three Juſtices, the which are (by <hi>Henry Bracton</hi>) called <hi>Itinerants,</hi> and in <hi>Brittons</hi> Book, <hi>Juſtices in Eire qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi errantes,</hi> as <hi>Gervas</hi> of <hi>Tilbery</hi> expoundeth it. The proper names of which Juſtices are ſet down by <hi>Roger Hoveden,</hi> who alſo deſcribeth their circuits, not to differ much from the ſame that our Juſtices of Aſſize do now ride.</p>
            <p>And ſo I conclude, that not only during all the time of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour himſelf, of <hi>William</hi> his ſon, and of his other ſon <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, (which was a peaceable Prince, and a maintainer of the antient Laws, and <hi>learned</hi> in them, whereof he had the name <hi>(Beauclark)</hi> but alſo under the government of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> and of this <hi>Heury</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond there was one Court follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115614:31"/>the King, which was the place of Soveraign juſtice, both for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Law and conſcience; and one other ſtanding Court which was Governeſs only of the lands and revenues of the Crown, The firſt of which was then called <hi>Curia Domini Regis &amp; Aula regia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bract. fol.</note> for that the Prince himſelf did many times fit in perſon there, and had Juſtices <hi>(a latere ſuo reſidentes)</hi> as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, namely, his chiefe Juſtice, Chancellour, Conſtables, Marſhall, and others. The later was then (as it is now) cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed <hi>Scac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carium eo quod luſibilis Scaccarii formam haberet.</hi> If you will give credit to <hi>Garveſ. Tilber.</hi> or elſe it took the name of <hi>Statarium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eo quod ſtabilis et firma effect ibi</note> as <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> and (after him) <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> doth write of it and in this the Prince ſate, not perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally at any time, but his chiefe Juſtice as Preſident, and then the Chancellor of the Exchequer the Treaſurer and Barons.<note place="margin">The Common Place.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And in this manner that high
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115614:31"/>Court of the King continued untill that <hi>Henry</hi> the third in the 9. yeare of his raign (which was about the time in which he aſpired to the age of xxi, years) granted unto his ſubjects that great Charter of the liberties of England in the 11. <hi>Ca.</hi> whereof he ordained thus, <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia placita non ſequuntur curiam noſtram, ſed teneantur in aliquo loco certo:</hi> whereupon followed two things, The firſt,<note place="margin">This Court, was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before this ſtatute it doth not appeare that it was then newly e. rected by the ſtat. of M. <hi>Ch.</hi>
               </note> that this Court was directed for the determination of all ſuch pleas as did not concern the Crown and dignitie of the Prince but were meerly civill, and did belong unto the ſubjects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves. The ſecond, that this Court was eſtabliſhed in a place certain (and that was at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) to the end that the people might have a ſtanding Seal of Juſtice wher to they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort for the tryall of their owne cauſes, and not to be driven to follow the King and his Court, but only where the matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115614:32"/>him.</p>
            <p>And after this,<note place="margin">fo. 105.108.</note> all the Writs that are recited in <hi>Henry Bractons</hi> book (which was written in the latter end of the raign of this King <hi>Henry</hi> the third) have this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment to the partie, <hi>quod ſit coram Juſticiariis meis apud Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaſterium,</hi> and not <hi>coram me vel Juſticiis meis,</hi> as the former form in <hi>Glanvill</hi> was.</p>
            <p>And thus began the Court, which (becauſe it hath power over Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas) wee now call the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Place. About this time alſo, or not long after, ſome other Courts of Juſtice were likewiſe opened,<note place="margin">The booke called <hi>Britton</hi>
               </note> as it may partly appear by <hi>Henry Bracton,</hi> but more plainly by <hi>John Britton,</hi> which followed immediatly after him, for in the beginning of the raign of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the firſt, this <hi>John Britton</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Hereford</hi> (whoſe name Mr. <hi>Bale</hi> in his Centuries (or his Printers) miſtaketh and calleth <hi>Bekton</hi>) being ſingularly learned
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115614:32"/>in the Laws of the Realm, did at the commandment of that King, and in his name) compile a book now imprinted and named <hi>Britton:</hi> in the beginning whereof he d vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all juriſdiction thus: Firſt, that the King himſelf had ſoveraign juriſdiction above all others in his Realm to Judge in all cauſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: Secondly that the Marſhall of the Kings houſe had the place of the King to hear and determine the pleas of the Crown within the verge, and that the Juſtices in <hi>Erie</hi> had like authority in every County once in 7. years. Thirdly, that the Juſtices which followed the King whereſoever he went and ſate in his place, had conuſance of erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgement, Appeals, and other matters of the Crown. Fourthly, That the Coroner of the Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold had his proper power within the verge and that he and others had the order of weight and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure throughout the Realm. Fiftly, That Sheriffs, Coroners, Hundre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115614:33"/>Burgeſſes, Serjeants and Beadles, had (and ſo have) their Courts within each of their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular limits. Sixthly, That Juſtices (being continually at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>) have power over Common Pleas. Seventhly, That the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> had authority concerning the Kings Debts and Feeds, and all things incident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. And Laſtly, that other Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had the charge of Aſſize of the deliverance of Gaols in every County,</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as after this diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of power to hold plea thus made: ſome of theſe Courts would not contain themſelves within their appointed limits, but ſought to enlarge their authority, by uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juriſdiction that was appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to others.<note place="margin">Articuli ſuper Chartas ca. 3, 4, 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame King did by Parliament (holden in the xxviii yeare of his raign) confirm that great Charter for ever, and in certain articles (as he did call them) ſet forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115614:33"/>the ſaid Charter: did then by like authority of Parliament enact, that they of the Exchequer ſhould not take knowledg of any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Plea: That the Seneſchall (or Steward) and the Marſhall of the Kings houſhould ſhould not have plea in hearing of treſpaſſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneſchall</hi> oſ <hi>Sein,</hi> a houſe and <hi>Scale</hi> ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. So ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, of <hi>Stow</hi> a place and <hi>Wear</hi> a keeper:</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and covenants made within the verge; And the Chancellors and the Juſtice of the Kings Bench (now the upper Bench) ſhould follow him whereſoever he went, to the end that he might alwaies have men about him that were able to deliver Law to ſuch as ſhould require it.</p>
            <p>Hitherto (as you ſee) there is no expreſs mention in <hi>Britton</hi> either of the Court of Admiralty, the Conſtables Court, or the Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and therefore it remayneth that we labour to find out from whence they alſo fetched their beginnings and that ſhall we the more eaſily do, if we give heed to this that <hi>Britton</hi> hath already opened, for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115614:34"/>he leaveth the ſoveraign juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all cauſes in the King,<note place="margin">The Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y. The Brittiſh and Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on Kings had their Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, as <hi>Etheldred</hi> who began his raign <hi>978 Edw.</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> had <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld</hi> for In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>lor. <hi>Edg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ph</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ded</hi> and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> had <hi>Turk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull.</hi> and K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ag <hi>Athe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtone</hi> had <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faid</hi> for his Chan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lor <hi>Cooke 4. Inſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 97.</hi> and <hi>Ethel ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> had <hi>Turketill</hi> for his Chancelor. about <hi>718.</hi>
               </note> ſo that whatſoever the King hath parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly de ivered out to others, his Juſtices Commiſſioners and Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats, that ſtill remaineth in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and was exerciſed either by himſelf in perſon, or by his Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, Councellors of a State, and Juſtices of Law that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally attended on him for that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>And therefore firſt concerning the Admiralty, I think that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of <hi>marine</hi> cauſes was not put out of the Kings houſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted over to the charge of the Admirall untill the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, whereunto I am led partly.</p>
            <p>And then (after this ſubſcription of him and his Queene, and of the Archbiſhops and Abbots) one <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibaldus</hi> is named <hi>Cancelarius:</hi> and in the end of all, after the date of the Chreme it is vvritten thus, <hi>Siwardus Notarius ad vicem Reni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baldii
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115614:34"/>Regiae dignitatis Cancellarii, hanc cartam ſcripſi &amp; ſubſcripſi;</hi> The next year after this King <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Conquerour gave (by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Charter) to the ſame Abby ſundry Lands in exchange for <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> the which King <hi>Edward</hi> had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on them; and in the end of this grant he likewiſe ſaith; <hi>Ego Willielmus Dei Gratia Rex &amp; Dux Normannorum atque Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps Cenomannorum hoc ſcribi pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipi &amp; ſcriptum hoc ſigno deminicae crucis</hi> † <hi>confirmando ſtabilivi no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraeque imaginis ſigillo inſuper aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari curavi.</hi> And then (in order as before) it followeth, <hi>Ego Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus Regis Cancellarius favendo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legi &amp; ſigillavi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereby it appeareth that the office of the Chancellor then was at the firſt to make and ſeal the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments that paſſed from the Prince, and this I call his originall duty, becauſe it cannot credibly be ſhewed of any hiſtory (as I think that ever there was in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115614:35"/>any of ſealing of writings or mention of the name of Chancellor, before the dayes of this <hi>Edward,</hi> who (having ſpent agreat part of his age in <hi>Normandy</hi>) firſt brought the uſe of the Seal from thence into this Nation,<note place="margin">See before of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of Chancelors</note> and with it (I ſuppoſe) the name of Chancelor, In whoſe time alſo <hi>Leofricus</hi> the <hi>Britain</hi> is the firſt Chancelor I find named.</p>
            <p>For that we learned of the Normans our manner of ſealing, <hi>Ingulphus</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Croyland</hi> (which came out of <hi>Normandy</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Train of the <hi>Norman</hi> Conquerour) aſſureth us, writing thus, <hi>Normancii Cyrographorum confectionem, cum crucibus aureis &amp; aliis ſignaculis ſacris in Anglia formari ſolitam, in Cerae impreſſionem mutant &amp;c.</hi> And that the name of him that kept the ſeal came out of <hi>France,</hi> alſo it may be probably conjectured both by the word (which we found nearer to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation of the French than of the Latin) and alſo by the office it
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115614:35"/>ſelf, which hath been exerciſed in <hi>France</hi> (under the ſame name and nature that we uſe it) ever ſince the time of <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> at the leaſt.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is manifeſt that the Chancelor did bear this name, and had the Charge of the Kings ſeal and writings both before and in the reign of the Conquerour, the which alſo (without all doubt) he hath ever ſince continued.</p>
            <p>Howbeit when I ſay (writings) I do not mean, he had the authority of making originall writs here before the time of the Conqueſt, for thoſe came out of <hi>Normandy</hi> alſo, as the very forms of the moſt of them (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expreſſed in the book of the <hi>Norman</hi> cuſtomes) may leade a man to think; and that rather alſo, becauſe the <hi>Saxons</hi> (our Anceſtors) whoſe proceedings in Judgment was <hi>deplano,</hi> and without ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did not uſe (ſo far as I have hitherto obſerved) to call the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by any writ or writing, but to ſend for them <hi>by certain Meſſengers,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115614:36"/>which they tearmed <hi>Theins,</hi> that is to ſay, Miniſters, or Serjeants, yea, and what that manner of ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by Writ was brought into uſe here, forthwith committed to the Chancellour; For Originall Writs of this time, had this form, <hi>Teſte Ranulpho de Glanvilla,</hi> &amp;c. Which was the name of the chief Juſtice of the Kings Court, then under whoſe ſealing they paſſed abroad.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs for as much as it is to be read in <hi>Bracton, quod omnia bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia de pace</hi> (which are prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons indeed) <hi>irrotulari debent in Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo de Cancellaria,</hi> and for that not onely the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the ſecond (which was made in the 15. year of King <hi>Edward the</hi> firſt, ſaith in plain words, that the <hi>for me donne in reverter ſatis eſt in uſu in Cancellaria,</hi> and hath often mention of the Clerks there; But alſo that other Statute of <hi>articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ſuper Chartas</hi> hath the expreſs names both of the Chancellour and Chancery, it muſt be confeſſed that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115614:36"/>the Chancellour had the keeping of the Rolls of Record, and the making out of Writs either at the ſame time that the common lace was erected, or not long after, that is to ſay, either under the reign of King <hi>Henry,</hi> the third, or elſe in the beginning of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, or elſe in the beginning of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the firſt, which later King (as Judge <hi>Priſot</hi> reporteth of him) la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured carefully to reduce our Law into order and writing, and, in mine opinion may therefore not unworthily be accounted our Engliſh <hi>Juſtinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit that the Houſe of the <hi>Rolles,</hi> which hath been of long time as it were, the Colledge of the Chancery men, was builded at the firſt by the ſame King <hi>Henry</hi> the third for another purpoſe, namely for the ſuſtentation of ſuch Jews as would give their names to Chriſt, and was thereof called, <hi>Dominus Judeorum converſorum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. Paris</note> yet that hindreth not, but that the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115614:37"/>ſame Houſe might ſhortly after be converted to another uſe, upon experience (as it is likely) that ſew converts was found amongſt the Jews to inhabite it; and then thus have you the Chancellour (or now inſtead of him the Commiſſioners) furniſhed with the Seal of Grace, and Seal of common Juſtice, and with him or them the Chancery for the keeping of Records, and the Clerks thereof for the framing of Writs;<note place="margin">Coment. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>43.</note> and as touching the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Judgement, I ſee not what Juriſdiction he had (his Court of Equity and ſome powers given by late Statutes onely excepted) which is not incident to the making or keeping of Records, for he could not reform the errour of another Court: yea, errour committed in his own Court was reverſed in the Bench of the King, now called the upper Bench. Neither could he try any Iſſue taken before him;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4 E. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> For that alſo was and is to be done in the upper Bench as a thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Juriſdiction.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115614:37"/>
            <p>It remaineth then that I ſpeak of this Court of Equity which (in my opinion) is not altogether ſo anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as others;<note place="margin">Oſ the high Court of Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery.</note> for (as you have heard before) King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt and the Parliament took order, that the Chancellour ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the King, even as the Juſtices of the Bench did, to the end that he might alwaies have at hand, all men for his direction in Suits that came before him, the meaning hereof (as I think was) that the Juſtices ſhould inform him of the Law, and the Chancellour of Equity; for (otherwiſe) I ſee not what uſe he could have of the Chancellour in this behalf: but onely for that he being commonly a Biſhop, or other Spirituall perſon (was the more meet) after the opinion of men in thoſe dayes) to give advice accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to equity and conſcience.</p>
            <p>In which reſpect alſo he was vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor for the King, and beſtowed his Benefices, ſo that ſuch as then ſought relief by Equity, were Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115614:38"/>to the King himſelf, who (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſiſted with the Chancellour and Counſell) did mitigate the ſeverity of Law in his own perſon, when it pleaſed him to be preſent, and did (in abſence) either refer it to the Chancellour alone, or to him and ſome others of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</p>
            <p>And this continued (if I be not miſtaken) untill the 20th. year of the reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, in which year (when he made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for his wars in <hi>France</hi>) it was enacted by Parliaments that the Chancellour and Treaſurer ſhould determine all complaints againſt <hi>extortion of Officers, mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> imbracery, and ſuch <hi>like of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences,</hi> and albeit that (indeed this authority be neither granted to himſelf alone, nor doth plainly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect any Court of Equity, yet for as much as it is the very firſt ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall power of this ſort, that I find committed to him from the King (in which alſo it is to be thought,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115614:38"/>that the proceeding was extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and abſolute, even as the Kings own before was,) I ſuppoſe it to be the laying of the firſt ſtone of the foundation of the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours Court. But after this (in the 36th. year of the ſame Kings reign) it was provided by Parliament; That if any were grieved contrary to the Articles of that Parliament, or others, That he ſhould have remedy in the Chancery without other Suit, by which Law the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour was not onely made ſole Judge in this newly erected Court, but was enabled ſo to proceed in Judgement after his own diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or (otherwiſe) the words <hi>(with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other Suits)</hi> were not Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall.</p>
            <p>After this alſo his authority was inlarged by ſundry Parliaments, as by one, to award damages upon untrue ſuggeſtion made before him: by another, To ſend Proclamation of Rebellion againſt ſuch as would not appear: And by others, To
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115614:39"/>grant Commiſſions of divers kinds, and to do many other things, whereof it is not needfull to make rehearſall here.</p>
            <p>And truly as theſe be firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings (that I can find) in Statute Law concerning this authority of Chancery Court, ſo alſo I do not remember, that in our reports of Common Law, there is any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of cauſes drawn before the Chancellour for help in Equity; but onely from the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, in whoſe dayes (by reaſon of thoſe Inteſtine trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles) <hi>Feofments to uſes</hi> did either firſt begin (as ſome have thought) or elſe did firſt grow common &amp; fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar as all men muſt agree for reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in which cauſes of <hi>uſes</hi> (chiefly) the Chancery Court was then fled unto, as to the onely Altar of help and refuge.</p>
            <p>But whence the Court of Equity took a beginning to be a diſtinct Court; I have made proof (as I think) that the power thereof was
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115614:39"/>alwaies in exerciſe, and conſidering that formerly all the Princes of this Realm, and now the Lord Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of this Nation is the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Miniſter of Juſtice under God, and ſworn to deliver to the people <hi>(aequam &amp; rectam Juſtitiam)</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee, how that it may otherwiſe be, but that (beſides his Court of meer Law) he muſt either reſerve to himſelf, or refer to others a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain preemment power, by the which he may both ſupply the want and correct the rigor of that poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (or written Law which (of it ſelf) neither is or can be made ſuch a perfect rule, as that a man may thereby ſquare out Juſtice in all cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that may happen.</p>
            <p>For written Laws muſt needs be made in a generality, and be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon that which happeneth for the moſt part, becauſe no wiſdome of man can foreſee every thing in particular, which in time experience doth beget, and therefore although the written Law be generally good and juſt, yet (in ſome ſpeciall caſe) it may have need of correction, by
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115614:40"/>reaſon of ſome conſiderable cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance (falling afterwards) which at the time of the Law making was not forſeen, whereas (otherwiſe) to apply one generall Law to all particular caſes, were to make all Shooes by one laſt, or to cut one Glove for all hands, which how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit it would prove, every man may readily perceive.</p>
            <p>And here of this Equity hath this name in Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>i. e. ſecundum,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>id eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniens; &amp; aſſimulatum;</hi> becauſe it doth not onely weigh what is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally meet for the moſt part, but doth alſo conſider the perſon, time, place, and other circumſtances, in every ſingular caſe, that cometh in queſtion, and doth thereof frame ſuch a judgement as is agreeable and convenient to the ſame, ſo that (in ſumme) the written Law is like a ſtiffe rule of Steel (or Iron) which will not be applyed to the faſhion of the Stone (or Timber) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto it is laid; and Equity (as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtole</hi> ſaith well) is like to the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115614:40"/>rule of the <hi>Leasbian</hi> Artificers which they might at pleaſure bend and bow to every Stone of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever faſhion.</p>
            <p>And hereby it may alſo appear, what uſe there ought to be aſwell of the poſitive (or written Law) as alſo of Equity it ſelf, for ſeeing that the poſitive or common Law, is made meet for the moſt part, and that Equity is added for help in few or ſingular cauſes, it followeth by reaſon, that commonly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly the poſitive Law, ſhould be put in ure, and that Equity ſhould be appealed unto, but onely in rare and extraordinary matters, leaſt on the one ſide, if the Judge in Equity ſhould take Juriſdiction over all, it ſhould come to paſs (as <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſaith) that the beſt ſhould bear rule (for ſo he calleth man whoſe judgement (if it be not reſtrained by the chain of Law) it is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carried away with unruly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and on the other ſide, if onely ſtreight Law ſhould be adminiſtred, the help of God (which ſpeaketh
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115614:41"/>in that Oracle of Equity, ſhould be denyed unto men that need it.</p>
            <p>And therfore even as two Hearbs being in extreamity of heat, or Cold be (by themſelves) ſo many poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and yet (if they be skillfully contempered) will make a whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome medicine, ſo alſo would it come to paſs, if either this Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Government as they call it) by rigor of Law onely, or this Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall judgement, at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Commiſſioners onely ſhould be admitted, And yet if they be well compounded together, a moſt ſweet and Harmonicall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice will follow them.</p>
            <p>And as a good Chancellour then would not, ſo the Commiſſioners now will not make this Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Nullus recedat a Cancellaria ſine remedio,</hi> and ſo receive Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of every complaint, which ſhall be made before them upon whatſoever ſuggeſtion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by both overthrow the authority of the Courts of Common Law, and alſo bring in upon men ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115614:41"/>and uncertainty, as hardly any man ſhall know how, or when he ſhall hold his own aſſured, but they will rather have the Common Law to have her juſt honour, and not to be interrupted in her right courſe or current, and will yet withall provide that the Gate of mercy may be opened, in all cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Suit, to the end that (where need ſhall be) the rigor of right may be amended by the Judgement of Equity, in which behalf this our age hath greatly to thank God, for that by the Miniſtry of <hi>our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi>) he doth not onely leave to us the right uſe of the Courts of meer Law, but hath alſo hitherto placed in that Praetoritall Room (or Chancery) men no leſs lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the common Laws of the Nation, than accompliſhed with the skill of this moderation and equity.</p>
            <p>I ſee that occaſion is offered me, to enter into the handling of ſome few queſtious concerning the order of Chancery, and chiefly of this
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115614:42"/>one, whether it be meet that the Commiſſioners ſhould appoint un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves, and publiſh to others any certain rules or limits of equity or no? about the which men Godly and learned have differed in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; For on the one part it is thought as hard a thing to preſcribe equity any certain bounds, as it is to make one generall Law to be a meet mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Juſtice in all particular cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: And on the other ſide it is ſaid, That if it be not known afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand in what caſes they will reach forth their help, and where not, then neither ſhall the people be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured how or when they may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs their own in peace, nor the practiſer of Law be able to inform his Clyent what may become of his action, The later of which opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I hold to be the beſt, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the late Regulation of the high Court of Chancery (together with the Common Law) in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> the 22th. <hi>Anno</hi> 1654. by his Highneſs the Lord Protector and his Counſell:) For though equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115614:42"/>cannot be limited; yet as it puts an end to controverſies, it muſt have certain rules preſcribed to it, otherwiſe it can neither be called a Court, nor can the Suitors be certain of any relief to be had therein, which Court (were it ſo) would ſoon be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Becauſe this and the like matters be of more difficultie than that I may (with modeſty) take upon me to determine them. And for that alſo it is not my preſent purpoſe, to diſpute what is convenient to be done in any Court, but rather to diſcourſe the beginning, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the benifit of them all, I will onely wiſh this one thing. That before any motion ſhould be made for either the parties Plantiff or Defendant, 4. or 5. dayes notice thereof were left with the Clerk in Court on the other ſide, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that motion, that ſo he might not be put off to ſhew cauſe from day to day, which rather increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth trouble and charges, than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther furthereth the ſuit for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115614:43"/>or benefits the parties in their cauſe.</p>
            <p>Which thing whether it might be more couvenient than the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent manner of motions, I will leave to the judgement of ſuch as have more wiſdom to deviſe, and power to execute; And will ſum up the reſt of our Courts and make an end.</p>
            <p>The Court of the Dutchy (or County Palatine of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> (which is by a late Act of Parliament com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the cuſtody of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner) grew out of the grant of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third,<note place="margin">The Court for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The Dutchy Court, the juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is now commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner or Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. County <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Lanc.</hi> erected in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>50</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> and Iustices of Aſſiſes Gaole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery and of the Peace have been ſince the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of it. <hi>Cook lib. 4. f. 204. 205.</hi>
               </note> who firſt gave that Dutchie to his Son <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> and endowed it with ſuch royall rights as the County Palatine of <hi>Chester</hi> had. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as it was afterward extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the perſon of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. (by reaſon of the union of it with the Crown of the Realm) the ſame King (knowing himſelf more rightfully) Duke of <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> then King of <hi>England,</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to ſave his right in the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115614:43"/>whatſoever ſhould befall the Kingdom. And therefore he ſeparateth his Dutchy from the Crown, and ſetleth it ſo in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall perſons of himſelf and his heirs: as if he had been no King, (or Pollitique Body) at all, in which manner it indured during the reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, and of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6th. that were deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him. But when King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the 4th. had (by recovery of the Crown) recontinued the right of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> he feared not to appropriate that Dutchie to the Crown again, And yet ſo as he ſuffered the Court, and Officers to remain as he found them.</p>
            <p>And in this manner it came (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Crown) to King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th. who liking well of that policy of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth (by whoſe right he alſo obteined the Kingdom) made by ſeparation of the Dutchie as he hath done, and ſo left it to his poſterity.</p>
            <p>It appeareth in our Books of the Tearms of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 4th.<note place="margin">The Star Chamber.</note>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115614:44"/>and the Report of caſes, happening under the uſurpation of <hi>Richard</hi> the third.<note place="margin">This Court was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before <hi>28 E. 3. Cook lib.</hi>
               </note> That ſometimes the King and his Counſell; And ſometimes the Lord Chancellour and other great perſonages, did uſe to ſit Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall in the place (then and lately called) for that it is decked with certain Stats) the <hi>Star Chamber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as (be like) that Aſſembly was not ordinary, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the next King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th. and his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. took order by two ſeverall Laws; That the Chancellour aſſiſted (with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there named) ſhould have power to hear complaints againſt <hi>Reteinors, Embraceries, miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> of Offices and ſuch other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which through the power and countenance of ſuch as do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them) (do lift up the head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other faults) and for the which inferiour Judges are not ſo meet to give correction.</p>
            <p>And becauſe that place was before time dedicated to the like ſervice, it hath ever ſince alſo been ſo uſed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115614:44"/>untill it was taken away in the late King <hi>Charls</hi> his reign.<note place="margin">The Court of Requeſts</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Court of the Requeſts being of the ſame nature (as I ſaid) with the Chancery took beginning by Commiſſion from King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. before which time the Maſters of the <hi>Requeſts</hi> had no warrant of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Juriſdiction,<note place="margin">This Court had no warrant by act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl ſhit. <hi>Cook lib. 4. fol. 97.</hi>
               </note> but travailed between the Prince and Petitioners, by direction from the mouth of the King.</p>
            <p>The ſame King alſo eſtabliſhed one Court of Preſident and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in the Marches of <hi>Wales</hi> 34. &amp; 35. H. 8.<note place="margin">The Court of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Wales</hi> and that of the North parts were taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the late K <hi>Ch.</hi> his reign. <hi>Anno 17. Car.</hi>
               </note> And another like Court of Preſident and Counſell in the North parts, which Court in <hi>Wales</hi> was a Court of Law in its principall Juriſdiction, although it did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all exerciſe other powers of equity. by vertue of other ſeverall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions that did accompany the ſame, and the Court of <hi>York</hi> was in its principall Juriſdiction Equity, and did exerciſe other powers by vertue of other Commiſſions.<note place="margin">Court of Wards.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Court of Wards began about
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115614:45"/>the 32th. year of the reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8, who alſo (in the next year after) added thereto the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſters of the Liveries, and withall conjoyned the names, ordaining that it ſhould be called, The Court of <hi>his Wards and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame King likewiſe had ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted one Court of the generall Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiours of his Lands; and one other of the Augmentations and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of his Crown; and a third Court of the firſt fruits and Tithes of Benefices. But all theſe were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards diſſolved and (by Queen <hi>Mary</hi>) united to the Court of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer. Thus having run along theſe Courts deriving them from the Crown, I might proceed yet further to ſhew the originall and beginnings of ſome Courts erected by the late Parliament, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and beginning of the High Court of Juſtice that was erected in <hi>Westminſter</hi> Hall <hi>Anno</hi> 1648. but they being ſo freſh in the memory of this age, I ſhall not need to make mention thereof.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
